Guide to the Robert Earl Cushman Papers, 1915; 1941-1988 UA.29.02.0159
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Professional Activities, 1947-1984; 2
  - Second Vatican Council, 1963-1971; 8
    - News Bulletins: Fourth Session, 1965 (Box 16)
    - Bulletins: Dutch Documentation Centre (DOC), 1965 (Box 16)
    - Bulletins: Divine Word News Service, 1963 (Box 16)
    - Bulletins: Divine Word News Service, 1965 (Box 16)
    - Bulletins: Divine Word News Service, 1964 (Box 17)
    - News Releases: Bureau of Information, National Catholic Welfare Conference, 1964 (Box 17)
- Writings, 1942-1987; 3
  Includes correspondence, memos, and other materials from the Wesley Works Project; course lectures; Divinity School addresses; other lectures; published articles; sermons; and letters to the editor. The series also contains a bound copy of Cushman’s unpublished 1942 doctoral dissertation on Plato, and a copy of The Heritage of Christian Thought; Essays in Honor of Robert Lowry Calhoun (1965). It also contains a few files of research materials. Arranged into three subseries: Wesley Works; Course Lectures; and Articles, Speeches, and Other Writings.
  - Wesley Works, 1960-1987; 9
    Includes correspondence, memos, financial reports, proofs; and other materials related to the Wesley Works Project of Oxford University Press. Files are arranged chronologically.
    - Wesley Works Editorial Project - Publicity, 1960-1964 (Box 17)
    - Organization of the Wesley Works Editorial Project, 1960-1967 (Box 17)
    - Reports on Contributions, 1960-1973 (Box 17)
    - Abingdon Press - Emory S. Bucke, 1960-1963, 1970 (Box 17)
    - Unfinished Business, 1961-1973 (Box 17)
    - Editorial Board, 1961-1975 (Box 17)
    - Oxford Press, 1961-1977 (Box 17)
    - Minutes, 1961-1966, 1971 (Box 17)
    - Editorial Consultants, 1962-1966 (Box 17)
    - Wesley Works Working Papers, 1963-1965 (Box 17)
    - Wesley Works Meeting - Dallas, TX, 1964 (Box 17)
    - Drew University, 1965-1966, 1970 (Box 17)
    - Editorial Directors of the Oxford Edition of Wesley's Works, 1965-1974 (Box 17)
    - Copy Text Editor, 1966, 1969 (Box 17)
    - Wesley Works Editorial Project, 1967 (Box 17)
    - Wesley Works Editorial Project Meeting, 1967-1969 (Box 17)
    - Minutes: Board of Directors - Washington, D. C., 1969 (Box 17)
    - Personnel Information, 1970-1972 (Box 17)
    - Orlando G. Folsom - Financial Statements, 1972 (Box 17)
    - Editorial Conference, 1970 (Box 17)
    - Board of Directors - Nashville, TN, 1970-1971 (Box 17)
    - Heitzenrater, Richard P., 1975 (Box 17)
    - Wesley Works Editorial, 1970-1974 (Box 17)
    - Quillian, Joseph, 1971-1979; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Baker, Frank, 1972-1980 (Box 17)
    - Wesley Works, 1974-1976 (Box 17)
    - Wesley's Work vol. II - Page Front Copy, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Kresge Foundation Application, 1976 (Box 18)
    - Promotional Documents and Minutes, 1976-1977 (Box 18)
    - Incorporation, 1976-1977 (Box 18)
    - Wesley Works Editorial Project: Budget, 1976-1978 (Box 18)
    - Development Planning, 1976-1978 (Box 18)
    - Minutes and Bulletin, 1977-1978 (Box 18)
    - Teer, Dillard, 1977 (Box 18)
    - Committee on Calendar of Publications, 1978-1983 (Box 18)
    - Oxford Editions, 1980 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1987; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Course Lectures, 1942-1978, undated; 10
    Contains Cushman’s lectures for courses he taught at Duke Divinity School, Yale University, and the University of Oregon. This subseries is arranged in chronological order.
    - Christian Ethics and Problem of Evil, undated (Box 18)
    - (C. T. 20) I. Introduction, Theological Method, Man, 1942-1958 (Box 18)
    - Outline: Philosophy of Religion and Systematic Theology - Yale, 1942 (Box 18)
    - Systematic Theology Introduction and Theological Encyclopedia, 1942 (Box 18)
    - Theological Method, 1942 (Box 18)
    - Theology as Empirical Science - Macintosh Exposition and Critique, 1942-1943 (Box 18)
    - Doctrine of God, 1943 (Box 18)
    - Miscellany - Notes on Person of Christ, Work of Christ, 1943 (Box 18)
    - Sacraments and Immortality, 1943 (Box 18)
    - Systematic Theology Revelation, 1943 (Box 18)
    - Psychology of Religion, 1944-1945 (Box 18)
    - Christian Theology (C. T. 20) Former Introduction, 1946-1955 (Box 18)
    - Conceptions of Men in Western Thought, [1946?] (Box 18)
    - Philosophical Theology I (Former Notes), 1946-1955 (Box 18)
    - C. T. 20 (Present Notes: Parts I, II, III), 1948-1965 (Box 18)
    - Christian Theology, 1948 (Box 18)
    - II. 19th Century Theology, 1951 (Box 19)
    - C. T. 20 II., 1951-1955 (Box 19)
    - Theology and Philosophy in the 19th Century I., 1951, 1955 (Box 19)
    - Philosophical Theology I - Revised Notes, 1952-1958 (Box 19)
    - Philosophical Theology, 1954, 1956 (Box 19)
    - C. T. 20 Moody Smith's Notes, 1955; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Seminar in 20th Century Theology, 1955 (Box 19)
    - Platonism and Christianity, 1956-1959 (Box 19)
    - Christian Theology C. T. 32, 1957-1969 (Box 19)
    - Philosophical Theology 325-326 Records and Program, 1972-1977 (Box 19)
    - Philosophical Theology, 1973 (Box 19)
    - Philosophical Theology, 1974-1975 (Box 19)
    - C. T. 325-326 Philosophical Theology, 1976-1977; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Philosophical Theology I Plato, 1978 (Box 19)
  - Articles, Speeches, and Other Writings, 1944-1986, undated; 11
    Contains addresses, lectures, and sermons; as well as articles, letters to the editor, bound journals, a copy of The Heritage of Christian Thought; essays in honor of Robert Lowry Calhoun (1965), Cushman’s doctoral dissertation, and a few files of research materials. Files are arranged alphabetically by title or subject of the work.
    - Biblical Elections as Sacred History, 1975 (Box 19)
    - Christology - Bultmann and Knox (Published Paper), 1958 (Box 19)
    - Church Doctrinal Standards, 1975 (Box 19)
    - The Church and the Theological Task - Methesco Address - May 21, 1979 (Box 19)
    - The Church and Theological Education (I), undated (Box 19)
    - The Church and Theological Education (II), undated (Box 20)
    - The Church and Theological Education (III), undated (Box 20)
    - The Church and Theological Education (IV), undated (Box 20)
    - Commencement Address - William and Mary College, VA, 1967 (Box 20)
    - Constitution on the Church: Iliff Lectures, 1967 (Box 20)
    - Constitution on the Church: Iliff Lectures, undated (Box 20)
    - Constitution on the Church: Lecture I, Iliff School of Theology, 1967 (Box 20)
    - Constitution on the Church: Lecture II, Iliff School of Theology, undated (Box 20)
    - Constitution on the Church: Lecture III, Iliff School of Theology, undated (Box 20)
    - Critique of Paper by Harold De Wolf, [American Theological Society], 1958 (Box 20)
    - Davies, W. D. - Commentary on Paul, 1974-1975 (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Lectures): Lecture I (Section 2) Original, 1976 (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Lectures): Lecture I (Original), undated (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Lectures): Original Lectures 2, 3, 4 for Shelton Smith, undated (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Lectures): Lecture II (Original) (with Revision?), undated (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Lectures): Lecture II (Original), undated (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Lectures): Lecture III (Original) - Divine Grace and Human Responsibility, 1976 (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Lectures): Lecture IV Original, undated (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Lectures): Reformation - Wesley Notes - New Lecture IV, undated (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Book Chapters): Chapter I (Revised), 1976 (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Book Chapters): Chapter V - Final Form - Calvin - 2nd Copy (Original and 1 copy), undated (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Book Chapters): Chapter III Cicero on Divine Sovereignty (Final), undated (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Book Chapters): Chapter IV - Divine Sovereignty - Augustine - Latest (2nd Copy and MSS), 1976 (Box 20)
    - Divine Sovereignty and Human Responsibility (Book Chapters): Chapter IV - Omnipotence and Foreknowledge of God - Augustine, undated (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: 50 Years of Theology at Duke - Convocation Addresses, 1977 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Cushman - Address Divinity School Alumni, 1970 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Dean's Desk, 1969 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Dean's Address to Senior Class, 1962, 1964-1965, undated (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Dean's Discourse, 1966-1970 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Dean's Discourse, 1969 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Dean's Discourse, 1970 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Dean's Reflections on the 40th Year of the Divinity School Alumni Association Luncheon, 1965 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Dean's Statement on "Moratorium", 1969 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Cushman Address - Martin L. King Memorial, 1968 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Opening Convocation - Divinity School Talks and Themes, 1965 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Opening Convocation, 1963 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Opening Convocation, 1965 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Opening Convocation, 1966 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Opening Convocation, 1967-1968 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Opening Convocation, 1968-1969 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Opening Convocation, 1969 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Opening Convocation: "Worship, Our Ministry", 1970 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School: Orientation Address, 1965 (Box 20)
    - Divinity School Summer Clinic Lectures: Crisis of Tradition; Crisis of Authority; Crisis of Worship, 1970 (Box 20)
    - Duke Divinity School Review (1 of 2), 1970-1971, 1976-1978 (Box 20)
    - Duke Divinity School Review (2 of 2), 1970-1971, 1976-1978 (Box 21)
    - The Ecumenical Challenge to Methodism, 1965 (Box 21)
    - The Enpersonalization of Worship, undated (Box 21)
    - Faith and Buildings, 1975 (Box 21)
    - Freedom and Choice in Plato and Augustine, 1979 (Box 21)
    - Gray Lectures et al., 1964-1966; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - The Heritage of Christian Thought: Essays in Honor of Robert Lowry Calhoun (Book), 1965 (Box 21)
    - Heritage of Christian Thought: Negotiations with Harper and Row, Calhoun - Festschrift, 1964-1965 (Box 21)
    - R. H. Calhoun - Festschrift Occasion, 1965 (Box 21)
    - Hippies in Theological Perspective, 1968 (Box 21)
    - Holy Spirit Miscellaneous Papers (Duodecim), 1952 (Box 21)
    - Is the Incarnation a Symbol? (Theology Today), 1958 (Box 21)
    - "The Jewish-Christian Encounter", 1966, 1969 (Box 21)
    - Kansas Lectures, 1963-1967, 1975 (Box 21)
    - Karl Barth and the Holy Spirit - Barth Outline Dogmatik, 1954 (Box 21)
    - "Lex Orandi, Lex Credenti" Published, 1962 (Box 21)
    - Methodist Bishops' Pastoral Letter: First Draft - In Defense of Creation: A Foundation Document on the Nuclear Crisis and Just Peace, 1984 (Box 21)
    - Methodist Bishops' Pastoral Letter: Political Comment and Action - Clippings, 1984-1986 (Box 21)
    - Methodist Bishops' Pastoral Letter: Letter to Methodist Bishops, 1984-1985 (Box 21)
    - Methodist Bishops' Pastoral Letter: Emendations, 1985-1986 (Box 21)
    - Methodist Bishops' Pastoral Letter: Letter to Council of Bishops, 1984-1986 (Box 21)
    - Methodist Bishops' Pastoral Letter: Bishops' Replies to Open Letters, 1984-1985 (Box 21)
    - Methodist Bishops' Pastoral Letter: Bishops' Letter and Response, 1986 (Box 21)
    - The Methodist Church and the World Council of Churches: Address to Council of Bishops, 1957 (Box 21)
    - The Methodist Discipline - Rewrite Paragraphs 301-314, 1974 (Box 21)
    - A Modern Revolt Against Kant, 1944 (Box 21)
    - Mutual Responsibility of Church and Seminary in Education for Ministry, 1969 (Box 21)
    - New Testament Faith and Mind of Church Today, undated (Box 21)
    - North Carolina Annual Conference Ordination Sermon, 1979 (Box 21)
    - Not-Being and the Problem of Evil in Plato (Doctoral Dissertation), 1942, 1980 (Box 22)
    - Doctoral Dissertation: Explanation Letter, 1980 (Box 22)
    - Palestine in Religious and Political Perspective Lebanon Valley Coolege, PA, 1972 (Box 22)
    - Palestine: Cushman Commentary - Erwin, Sam, open letters, etc., 1973-1976 (Box 22)
    - Palestine: Addresses and Talks, undated (Box 22)
    - Pastoral School Lecture (Oklahoma), 1989 (Box 22)
    - Place of Wesley in the Christian Tradition - Drew University, 1974 (Box 22)
    - Preface - Religion and World Politics, University of Oregon Lectures in Religion, 1945 (Box 22)
    - The Problem of Miracle, 1957 (Box 22)
    - A Protestant Understanding of Justification by Faith, 1963-1964 (Box 22)
    - Purpose of Christian Education - Allentown, PA, 1947-1948 (Box 22)
    - Radio Talks - Methodist Hour, 1949 (Box 22)
    - Reconciliation Yesterday and Today, 1969 (Box 22)
    - Roman Catholic Renewal and Vatican Council II: A Protestant Observer's View (Review and Exposition), 1967 (Box 22)
    - "Sacred Secularity" Clemson, 1969 (Box 22)
    - Second Vatican Council's Meaning to Methodists: 1) Kentucky Wesleyan, 2) Pfeiffer College, 1966 (Box 22)
    - The Shape of Christian Faith (Iliff Review), 1956 (Box 22)
    - 6 Lectures on the Christian Faith, 1956 (Box 22)
    - Stewardship Seminar - General Board of Lay Activities, Chicago, 1967 (Box 22)
    - Theological Education and the Church, undated (Box 22)
    - Theology in the Evangelical Tradition, 1978 (Box 22)
    - Theological Reflections on Occasion of the Forthcoming Retirement of a Master Theologian and Teacher - Professor David Shipley, 1971 (Box 22)
    - Theological Perspective of Stewardship, 1969 (Box 22)
    - Theological Trends Today and the Nature of the Church, 1958 (Box 22)
    - Toward a Revised Theological Method Duodecim, 1968 (Box 22)
    - Vision, Vocation, and Authority - Baccalaureate Sermon on Retirement, 1971 (Box 22)
    - Wesley Lectures and Methodism, undated (Box 22)
    - West Virginia Conference Lectures, undated (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous Writings and Off-Prints, 1945-1976 (Box 22)
    - Addresses to Annual Conferences (Miscellaneous), 1960-1961 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous Papers and Sermons, 1968-1982 (Box 22)
    - Sermons - Ruth Petry - Davies Library (Miscellaneous Sermons), 1962-1981 (Box 23)
    - Wainwright, Geoffrey: Bibliography (Research), 1982 (Box 23)
    - God Is Dead - Theology - Clippings (Research), 1965-1966 (Box 23)
    - H. Leonard - Bibliographies (Research), 1973-1980 (Box 23)
    - Occasional Addresses (Unpublished), 1947-1954 (Box 23)
    - Occasional Lectures - Christology, 1957-1961 (Box 23)
- Personal Files, 1915, 1941-1988; 4
  Contains correspondence with family, friends, colleagues, and former students; as well as photographs, pamphlets from church celebrations, and other memorabilia. Cushman also collected some papers created by Duke Divinity School professor H. Shelton Smith. Arranged into two subseries: Personal Correspondence; and Documents and Memorabilia.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1945-1988, undated; 12
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent or subject of the correspondence.
    - Correspondence A-G, 1975-1987 (Box 23)
    - Agorides, Savas, 1968-1976 (Box 23)
    - Annual Conference Retirement, 1979 (Box 23)
    - B Correspondence, undated (Box 23)
    - Bailey, Lloyd, 1988 (Box 23)
    - Barr, Browne, 1968-1979 (Box 23)
    - Bernabeo, Paul: Encyclopedia of Religion, 1983 (Box 23)
    - Bucke, Emory Stevens, 1965-1975 (Box 23)
    - Cannon, William, undated (Box 23)
    - Carlton, John William, Rev., Dr., 1989 (Box 23)
    - Christmas Greeting Replies, 1960 (Box 23)
    - Christmas Greeting Replies, 1961 (Box 23)
    - Christmas Greeting Replies, 1971 (Box 23)
    - Cleland, James T., 1971-1979 (Box 23)
    - Cole, Anne Curtis, 1981-1983 (Box 23)
    - Cushman, Commendation of, 1959-1960 (Box 23)
    - Cushman, Robert E. (Uncle), 1967 (Box 23)
    - D, 1981, 1984 (Box 23)
    - Deanship, Letters of Congratulation, 1958; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Dunn, Van Bogard, 1981-1982 (Box 23)
    - F, 1980 (Box 23)
    - H, 1980-1982 (Box 23)
    - H-Mc, 1974-1986 (Box 23)
    - Henry, Stuart, 1979 (Box 23)
    - Herzog, Frederick, 1972-1985 (Box 23)
    - Hildebrandt, Franz, 1982-1986 (Box 23)
    - Hill, Sam S.: Dictionary of Southern Religion, 1981-1985 (Box 23)
    - Invitations, 1981 (Box 23)
    - J, 1981 (Box 23)
    - Jones, Jameson, 1981-1982 (Box 23)
    - L, 1980-1983 (Box 23)
    - Langford, Thomas (Dean), 1979-1984 (Box 23)
    - Letters on Retirement from Divinity School, 1979-1980 (Box 23)
    - M-Q, 1975-1985 (Box 23)
    - The Methodist Publishing House and Abingdon Press, 1959-1970 (Box 23)
    - Meyers, Eric, 1982 (Box 23)
    - Nasir, Elizabeth and President - Birzeit College, 1972-1976 (Box 23)
    - Nelson, W. Fletcher, 1974-1981 (Box 24)
    - P, 1980-1982 (Box 24)
    - Personal Letters, 1945-1949 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 1945-1977 (Box 24)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1960-1982; 13 folders (Box 24)
    - Personal Correspondence - Copies, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
    - Reception Responses: Bob and Barbara Cushman, 1979 (Box 24)
    - Q, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
    - Quick, William K., 1972-1974, 1989 (Box 24)
    - Quillian, Joseph Dean, 1979, 1982 (Box 24)
    - R, 1981 (Box 24)
    - R-U, 1975-1990 (Box 24)
    - S, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
    - Schafer, Thomas A., 1980 (Box 25)
    - Smith, H. Shelton, undated (Box 25)
    - Sommer, Gunter (Student), 1973-1987; 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Spence. Dr. Hersey E., 1960-1971 (Box 25)
    - Stiles, Elizabeth (Sister), 1960-1971 (Box 25)
    - V-Z, 1975-1982 (Box 25)
    - W, 1980-1981 (Box 25)
    - Y, 1980 (Box 25)
  - Documents and Memorabilia, 1915, 1941-1987, undated; 13
    - Photographs, undated (Box 25)
    - Photographs, 1963-1966 (Box 25)
    - Photos and Clippings, 1957-1979 (Box 25)
    - Old Documents (Lane), 1915 (Box 25)
    - Documents and Clippings, 1964-1971 (Box 25)
    - Documents: Personal and Institutional, 1970-1975 (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous Papers, 1971-1983, undated; 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Great Britain: Ecclesiastical Architecture, undated (Box 25)
    - Travel Guide - Great Britain, 1982 (Box 25)
    - Charles Robinson MSS, undated (Box 25)
    - James T. Cleland: Memorial Documents, 1978-1979 (Box 25)
    - 90th Anniversary South Meriden Methodist Church Brochure, 1941 (Box 25)
    - Nuclear Shelters, 1958-[1968?] (Box 25)
    - Osborn Documents, 1980-1984 (Box 25)
    - Trinity Church 150th Anniversary, 1982 (Box 25)
    - Voegelin - Pauline Vision of the Resurrection, 1975 (Box 25)
    - Wit and Humor, undated (Box 25)
    - H. Shelton Smith: General Correspondence, 1976-1985 (Box 25)
    - H. Shelton Smith: A Marriage Service for Linda and Keith, undated (Box 25)
    - H. Shelton Smith: Final Report on Worship and the Sanctuary of the United Church of Christ, undated (Box 25)
    - H. Shelton Smith: Reprints, 1956 (Box 25)
    - H. Shelton Smith: Christianity and Human Rights in a Changing South, 1979 (Box 25)
    - H. Shelton Smith: Nuclear Warfare, undated (Box 25)
    - H. Shelton Smith: North Carolina Council of Churches, 1982-1983 (Box 25)
    - H. Shelton Smith: Obituary and Other Papers, 1973-1987 (Box 25)
    - H. Shelton Smith: Memorial, 1979-1987 (Box 25)